Guide to the Art Libraries Society of North America Southeast Chapter Records, 1975-2017 and undated RL.00051
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Art Libraries Society of North America Southeast Chapter records
1975-2017 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Art Libraries Society of North America. Southeast Chapter
RL.00051
6.6 Linear Feet 3023 Items
ARLIS/SE was founded in 1974 as a chapter within the Southern Region of the Art Libraries Society of North America. The collection includes chapter correspondence, bylaws, annual reports, membership lists, photographs, conference materials, LoPresti Awards (for excellence in art publication), and financial records. Scattered throughout are materials and correspondence related to the national organization. There are 20 electronic files on one floppy disk that have been migrated to the electronic records server. There are 20 black-and-white photographs and two transparencies.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Art Libraries Society of North America Southeast Chapter Papers, 1975-2017 and undated were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002, 2015 and 2018.
Biographical Note
ARLIS/SE was founded in 1974 as a chapter within the Southern Region of the Art Libraries Society of North America (ARLIS/NA founded 1972, Chicago). Members primarily come from the states of North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, Georgia, Florida, Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, Puerto Rico, and the American Virgin Islands. A Regional Representative is appointed by ARLIS/NA to the Southern Region / SE Chapter and serves a two-year term. This Representative serves as a liaison between the Chapter and the Executive Board.
The Chapter is involved in several activities. It issues a Newsletter, now called ARTifacts, hosts an online discussion list and web site, and holds a Conference annually somewhere within the Southeast region. In addition, its members participate in the ARLIS/NA Annual Conference, including hosting the Annual Conference in the Southeast in 1996 (Miami Beach). A major activity of the Chapter is its LoPresti Publicatoin Award Competition, established in 1985 to recognize and encourage excellence in art publications issued in the Southeastern United States. This annual award is named for Mary Ellen LoPresti (d. 1985), who was the Design Librarian at North Carolina State University.
Collection Overview
The collection includes chapter correspondence, bylaws, annual reports, membership lists, photographs, conference materials, LoPresti Awards (for excellence in art publication), and financial records. Scattered throughout are materials and correspondence related to the national organization. There are 20 electronic files on one floppy disk that have been migrated to the electronic records server. There are 20 black-and-white photographs and two transparencies.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Correspondence, Financial Papers, Administrative Materials, Annual Conferences, Art Publication Awards, and Miscellaneous Papers.
Transparencies; Machine-readable records; Black-and-white photographs; Art Libraries Society of North America. Southeast Chapter; ARLIS/SE; ARLIS/NA; Art Libraries Society of North America
- Correspondence, 1975-1996 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  This series is first organized by creator, then chronologically.
  - Abell, Ray, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Abrams, Leslie, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Clayton, Bill, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Duncan, Marcia, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Friedman, Leslie, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Lo Presti, Maryellen, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Morse, Yvonne, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Patrick, Stephen, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Rees, Philip, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Ross, Anne, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Rushing, Darla, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Sloop, Jill, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Knoerr, Margaret, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Straight, Elsie, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Teague, Edward, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Wolf, Sara, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Zula, Floyd, 1989 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1980-2000; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership correspondence, 1996 and undated (Box 2)
  - Proposal (1991) for ARLIS/NA mtg. in Charleston, SC, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Invitation to ARLIS/NA 1996 Miami Beach, FL, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Sample letterhead and envelopes (blank), undated (Box 2)
- Financial Papers, 1978-2016 and undated
  - Finances, March, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Finances, 1993-1996; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Banking, 1978-1991; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Deposit Record, 2012-2013 (Box 9)
  - Receipt Book, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Receipt Books, 2008-2013 (Box 9)
  - Membership and Conference Receipt Book, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
  - SunTrust Business Accounts, 2002-2003 (Box 3)
  - ARLIS/SE Secretary/Treasurer, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Secretary/Treasurer Duties, undated (Box 3)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1978-1991 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer's Report and Grant Preparation, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer Invoices, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer Bank Account- NEXITY, undated (Box 3)
  - Treasurer checking South Trust, 1998-2003 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer checking Bancorp, 1998-2001 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer checking First Union, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer checking SunTrust, 2001-2004 (Box 3)
  - SunTrust Business Accounts, 2010-2016; 2 folders (Box 9)
- Administrative Materials, 1975-2017 and undated
  This series includes the bylaws for the Southeast chapter, annual reports of chapter happenings including newsletters, executive board documents, and membership materials.
  - Bylaws, 1976-2001
    - Bylaws, 1976-1991 (Box 3)
    - Bylaws-1991 Revision; Bylaws 1999-2000, 1991, 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - Bylaws: General Information Web Listing, 1998-2001 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1975-2017
    - ARLIS/NA Strategic Plan- Exec. Board approval, 1991 (Box 3)
    - ARLIS/NA Strategic Plan for 1996-1999 (Box 3)
    - Annual Reports, 1975-1992, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters, 1975-1997; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - ARTifacts, 1998-2001 (Box 3)
    - ARTIfacts, 2017 (Box 9)
  - Board Papers, 1984-1998
    - ARLIS/NA Chapter Officers List, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Conference/meeting minutes, 1984-1997 (Box 4)
  - Membership, 1977-2003 and undated
    - Membership Application Forms, 1980-1987 (Box 4)
    - ARLIS/NA Membership Directory Forms, 1992 (Box 4)
    - ARLIS/SE Mailing Lists and Menu's, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Membership Lists, 1977-1998; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Archives: Membership/Dues from Donna Smith, 2001 (Box 4)
    - ARLIS/NA member names sent to chapters, 2002 (Box 4)
    - ARLIS/SE Membership, 2003 (Box 4)
    - ARLIS/NA new members in Southeast chapter, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Membership Forms, 1998-1999; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - ARLIS/NA Mailings, 1977-1989 (Box 4)
    - Annual Meeting Notes/Mailings to Members, 1981 (Box 4)
    - ARLIS/NA Membership brochures, 1994 and undated (Box 4)
    - News of members phone calls, etc., 1981 (Box 4)
    - Membership, undated (Box 9)
- Annual Conferences, 1983-2017
  This series includes all documents related to Southeast and National chapter conferences. Files are first grouped by conference, then organized chronologically.
  - ARLIS/NA Annual Conference Planning, 1983 (Box 4)
  - National Conference Task Force, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Sarasota Conference Graphics for t-shirts, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Sarasota Conference photographs, 1985 (Box 4)
  - ARLIS/NA Conference Final Reports (15th Washington, D.C.), 1987 (Box 5)
  - ARLIS/SE Annual Conference, Raleigh, NC, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Charlotte Conference, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Tampa Conference, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Durham Conference, 1992 (Box 5)
  - ARLIS/SE Agenda Meeting, 1992 (Box 5)
  - ARLIS/NA Pre-Conference Meeting, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Birmingham Conference, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Birmingham Post-conference Meeting minutes, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Clemson Conference, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Augusta Conference, 1996 (Box 5)
  - ARLIS/NA Annual Conference Proceedings (24th- Miami Beach, FL), 1996 (Box 5)
  - ARLIS/NA Annual Conference Preliminary Program (San Antonio, TX), 1997 (Box 5)
  - New Orleans Conference, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Sarasota Conference Information, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Sarasota Conference photographs, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Pre-Conference survey, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Conference brochure (includes mock-up), 1999 (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Conference correspondence, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Conference registration, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Conference elections, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Conference speakers, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Conference miscellaneous, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Raleigh-Durham Conference, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Raleigh-Durham Conference membership, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - 27th Annual Conference, 2001 (Box 5)
  - Boca-Raton, FL Conference membership, 2002-2003 (Box 5)
  - Asheville Conference, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Asheville Conference membership, 2002-2003 (Box 6)
  - Conference Information, 2003 (Box 6)
  - New Orleans Conference, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Winston-Salem Conference, 2004 (Box 6)
  - Savannah, GA, Conference planning, 2009 (Box 9)
  - Cartersville, GA, Conference planning, 2010 (Box 9)
  - Durham, NC, Conference planning, 2011 (Box 9)
  - Athens, GA, Conference planning, 2012 (Box 9)
  - Sarasota, FL, Conference membership, 2016 (Box 9)
  - Savannah, GA, Conference planning, 2017 (Box 9)
  - Savannah, GA, Conference membership, 2017 (Box 9)
  - Savannah, GA, Conference tote bag, 2017 (Box 10)
  - Savannah, GA, Conference tote bag contents, 2017 (Box 9)
  - Savannah, GA, Conference student projects, 2017 (Box 9)
- Art Publication Awards, 1984-2014 and undated
  This series includes the LoPresti awards for art publications, as well as miscellaneous awards given by the chapter.
  - LoPresti Awards- Guidelines, 1984, 1991, 1999 (Box 6)
  - LoPresti Awards-Award and entry form graphics, 1992 and undated (Box 6)
  - LoPresti Awards- Raffle Tickets, undated (Box 6)
  - LoPresti Awards, 1985-1999; 15 folders (Box 6-7)
  - LoPresti Awards, 2013-2014 (Box 8)
  - Art Publication Awards, 1984-1990 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1981-2002 and undated
  - ARLIS/NA Chapter Duties and Procedures, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/SE name changes, etc., 1993 (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/NA funded projects, 1981, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
  - Secretary Minutes, 1994, 2000-2002 (Box 7)
  - Chapter Idea Exchange, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Idea Book for ARLIS/NA Chapter Officers, 1992 (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/NA Chapter Success Book, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Publicity, 1981 (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/NA Flyers, undated (Box 7)
  - Other Chapter meeting announcements and newsletters, 1980-1981; non-Southeast chapter materials (Box 7)
  - Archives Agreement Draft with Duke University, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Stationery Designs, undated (Box 7)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 7)
  - Black and white photographs, undated (Box 7)
  - Loose Material, 1992-1994; 2 folders (Box 7)